hey everybody casemirotori here we are
at the end of our kickstarter
promotional videos this is the last one
it's a two-parter if you haven't checked
out the kickstarter already please do
it's for a graphic novel meow the
infinite it's awesome we'd love to send
you a book or two please check it out
when you get a chance
this video is an invited lecture that i
gave to a company called infuria.io
and i submitted like a thing saying
please give me topics that that you'd
like me to cover and one of the things
that i saw in a lot of the topics that
came back was sort of this underlying
concept of like code kind of getting out
of control like being you know to huge
code bases and slow and underperforming
and so on
and so this was my attempt to give sort
of a general audience answer to the
question
where does bad code come from like where
do these problems come from
this is a two-parter the first part is
the lecture the second part will be the
q a so i hope you enjoy it and i'll be
back afterwards to talk about part two
where does bad code come from
we kind of know that it's everywhere
right now like
there's a sense if you have experienced
programming for a long time or if you
just in general look at the way things
are going from a
removed sort of more objective observer
standpoint you can see that there seems
to be a lot wrong with software today
and
first of all there's way too much code a
lot of the times even fairly simple
pieces of software now are like hundreds
of thousands of lines of code millions
of lines of code and so on uh they're
typically built in these
very very fragile build systems
oftentimes so complicated that they end
up having to be wrapped inside things
like docker containers or things like
this even to just try and get them to
keep running into the future because
they have so many crazy dependencies and
there's really no way to guarantee that
all the things will remain working or
will remain in lockstep as they move
forward
um when you actually do have everything
installed properly on your machine and
when you've finished having a package
manager install the language which
installs some package manager which then
goes and gets the packages which unpack
which install their own packages blah
blah after you manage to get all of that
going and you actually can run a build
the builds take forever sometimes things
like tensorflow or stuff like this that
a lot of people use that are very
popular projects seem to take hours to
build sometimes which is absolutely
incredible if you think about how much
power computers have today that the
things could take that long to build
when the actual software comes out the
other end the quality is not very high
there's a lot of sitting around waiting
for it to do things like load or
communicate with a network and it really
kind of just stalls while that's
happening and doesn't really let you do
very much
it's slow when it actually does things
things that probably should be much
faster on today's hardware are not
they're still quite slow
um it takes a ton of space as well so
not only do these programs now take up
huge amounts of space you have like 100
200 megabyte executables which is insane
and their working footprints are like
many gigabytes of memory even for doing
things that seem very simple like just
scrolling some 2d images or things that
are very basic nonetheless are taking
tremendous amounts of storage tremendous
amounts of memory it's just kind of very
odd that that would be going on and
finally it's not like software got
tremendously more reliable or something
else happened it's still totally buggy
and it has all the same problems if not
more problems than it has always had
before it sort of jumped uh this level
of sort of kind of complexity and and
kind of in general this this overall uh
overriding sort of sense of decay that
seems to be seeping in
to whatever we call the software
industry currently
and so
thinking about this if we want to
actually try and talk about where bad
code comes from we have to start making
some judgment calls about what do we
mean when we say bad code anyway i can
talk about all those things and and
complain about stuff but if i don't
really have some kind of a more specific
understanding of what it really is that
i'm talking about
it's not going to be possible for us to
like get anywhere we can't really get
anywhere fixing the problem we're just
sort of saying that the problem exists
which is great but we do have to then
figure out how are we going to move
forward so i'm going to make a little
bit of a judgment call here and say when
i'm talking about bad code or what we
should be concerned about with bad code
it doesn't really have much to do with
money if you're talking about wanting to
make money i don't think the current
environment anyway at least for the time
being
really cares that much about the quality
of your code i think there's so little
competition in the software space right
now because there's so much software to
write we're still relatively early in
the evolution of software there's still
so many places you can take software too
that there isn't a lot of market
pressure to ship high quality stuff a
lot of times consumers
or whoever your customers are are
choosing between a very small field of
options so being someone who ships a
quality product while it may be a
tremendous competitive advantage if you
do it
will not exactly be a requirement
competitively because other people are
not shipping quality software so you
really don't need this to make money yet
you might in the future but i'm not
gonna try and make an argument that you
need to do this uh for your financial
well-being of your company or your
career whatever or anything like that
and i'm also not claiming that people
aren't having fun or anything like that
they might not be it may be that current
software practices are really not fun
for them but it could be that you know
you just drop on your vr goggles and you
you download a bunch of frameworks and
you get them all called together
eventually and you just play around with
it and you had fun and it was okay right
who knows right so i'm not going to
claim either of those two things because
i don't think
there's really any need to go down that
route because all i'm trying to talk
about when we talk about bad code is
like
what's our potential like like what
could we be doing what could we be doing
engineering-wise
versus where we currently are are we
performing up to that potential at all
or are we actually kind of falling
pretty far behind
where we could be if we looked at what
we could be delivering to our customers
and to society if we took things more
seriously right so i don't think we have
to do this
it's just if you care about quality
what are we talking about here so that's
what i mean when i say bad code i say
we're looking at something that seems
like boy we should be able to do a lot
better than this
why aren't we right
now it's important to distinguish
between two things
i actually think
as an industry we haven't done that
poorly on algorithms
algorithms are actually understood in
some pretty profound ways i think the
people who have done all the work
figuring out like order notation and
what the complexity classes of things
are and you know they haven't proved
whether p equals np yet or whatever
but at the end of the day
there's a lot of stuff we know like we
know how to analyze hash tables and how
to think about them we know
uh like what the properties are of a
heap or what different sorting
algorithms will do like we have a lot of
ways of thinking about algorithms and
furthermore a lot of the advice you see
about algorithms may not be awful like
it's possible that in general you can
experience algorithms in a pretty sane
way you can be taught algorithms in the
same way
you can think about them the same way
that's actually i don't think all that
unusual so if i was to put a pin you
know if i was trying to point a finger
and say this is the place that i think
that we're going wrong
algorithms and like the actual specific
idea of specifically how some piece of a
program is going to work algorithmically
it just doesn't seem like what we're
really talking about when we're talking
about the bulk of bad code as we
perceive it or bad software as we
perceive it it's usually not like what
sorting you know algorithm did you
choose
usually what we're talking about is the
mess of the rest of the code we are
having a problem writing all the code
that glues these algorithms together
right like when we're talking about what
we're actually going to do here the
problem that we actually have is not so
much that like we couldn't sit down and
figure out what the proper algorithm is
here for this the problem seems to be
more that we can't figure out how to
connect these things or how to manage
the infrastructure into which these
algorithms are placed that seems to just
not work right it seems to be like that
is what's going off the rails
and so the question is how did we get
there
in the old days that really couldn't be
the case because there were hard
constraints on what you could ship when
a computer only has 64k of ram in it
right
there's no way for that glue code to
spiral out of control there's no way for
the infrastructure to be all that big to
begin with so there is a natural limit
on what could actually happen there and
it seemed to be working
to that effect nowadays we don't have
that
and it seems like we have never
developed any replacement for it
so the question is like
why and in order to understand why we
haven't developed a replacement for it
i'm going to have to talk a little bit
about how you actually learn to make
stuff like on a computer
and i realize it's going to sound very
trite maybe to people who are listening
to this who aren't programmers it won't
but to people who are programmers this
is gonna sound uh a little bit silly
right but please
think about it actually think about this
for a second because if you actually
think about it for a second you'll
realize that we all take it for granted
right we all take for granted that this
is going on and nobody talks about it
but we kind of need to right
so nobody's born knowing how to program
a computer right and and i know this
better than anybody because i learned a
program at a very early age but before i
could learn to program i actually
literally sat i was a little tiny child
i sat at a keyboard right that my
parents had my dad had i would just type
i would type gibberish into the computer
right and if you think about it like you
first learn to just input characters or
something into a computer and if you're
young enough they're literally just
garbage
but soon what you're doing is your brain
right is training itself up
to learn that only certain combinations
of letters right only certain syntax
will produce a result if you're using a
programming language this is why we call
them languages right they have grammar
they have syntax all this sort of stuff
right
and so something in your brain
and we're not advanced enough
technologically to know like what's
actually going on exactly but something
in your brain
is creating
a filter and a generator
something that's able to produce valid
syntax for a particular language
and also able to like you know throw out
ones of those that it wouldn't want or
wouldn't need or that don't get closer
to something right
it's got a metric
and so if you think about this in terms
of like ai research or something like
that right
there's a training process you have to
train up some generator to generate
things that are valid in the output
domain and then you need some kind of
filtering process that's going to take
and get you closer to whatever it is
that you're trying to achieve with that
generative process right and so this
builds and builds over time when you're
a programmer right it builds over time
and in your head you start to learn that
you can make new parts of this right
like functions and things like that or
get new ones from libraries and you're
starting to think at like a higher level
so that generator is now generating
things higher up and again filtering
things higher up
and then finally you look at experienced
programmers people in printer a long
time not necessarily good or bad just
experienced
their code just be very regularized
right so that filter has dialed in quite
a bit right they're throwing out a lot
of possible options that would be legal
in the language they're programming at
and only selecting from a very very
narrow set so that generator filter
process is producing highly regularized
very predictable things at that point
which we don't know what that means
right and we can't understand it at a
deep under like you know uh
physiological level
but what we do know is it means a huge
possibility space has been carved off
of that system
we all know that when we first learned
to type in babel like you know just the
literal syntax of the language
anything was possible right
you just type anything in that was legal
in the language and you could type it in
right
and over time you lose the ability to
type certain things in
and it's not like you couldn't force
yourself to
it's just you don't right
so you've tuned the generator and the
filter in your brain to just do a
certain narrow subset of things
and what we think when we think of
experienced programmer is that that was
good that was a good process now they're
producing like good code or something
right
i know it sounded silly hopefully though
when we get to the end there you're not
too disagreeing with me about the fact
that something like this must be going
on in our brains
so our brains have learned this filter
process this thing that's going on and
we all have a slightly different one
right
but anyone who's been programming for
any appreciation of time has formed this
somehow
now i like to think of this as a
metaphor uh in my brain i always kind of
think of it this way
because i don't really know how to think
about it and the way i think about it is
exploration right
i started out in my co-bases in some
sense and i think of that generator
process as sort of being like almost
like a navigator right like at any point
in time when i'm going to figure out
like what i'm going to do in the code
i'm sort of like thinking like it's like
dead reckoning a little bit it's like
well i think the answer is probably this
way i'm gonna try some things sometimes
i backtrack right
um and i'm i'm trying to navigate and
over time i'm trying to get to a
destination that i believe is somewhere
but i don't know exactly where it is
right and maybe you've had this feeling
as well like this kind of feeling like
you know it's it's sort of a journey
right it's not it's not like things the
metaphors people normally use don't
actually apply that well it's not like
architecture right it's not like other
things where we do a lot of solving
first and then just kind of
put it in there uml diagram people have
tried right but it doesn't seem to
really go that way it feels more like a
journey where we're not really sure
about the end result and we're trying to
get there right and maybe the better
programmers are kind of better at making
that journey and the newer programmers
who have a lot to learn that you know
it's worse right but it feels that way
to me it feels more like that
and we don't have maps right we're
navigators that don't know the lay of
the land so we're constantly trying to
like kind of figure out
as we go that's how i normally think
about it and i think about like you know
when we're you know setting off on these
things and looking for things they could
be very like uncharted we could be
trying to go somewhere that like no
one's ever gone before
or we might be just trying to do
something we do know pretty well and we
kind of understand the route but we
might do a little bit differently this
time because we know how the route went
last time and we think we could improve
it things like that right
now sometimes this works great we end up
in a place that we you know it's
fantastic it's everything we dreamed of
when we thought we were going to go
there
other times we just like forget it this
thing ain't shipping
ditch the boat take as much food as you
can walk across the iceberg and let's
hope uh that like we encounter another
human being before we all die right
so you know it it
it has sort of the same analogies in a
way the way it ends is similar to the
way uh journeys end in the real world
too sometimes
now the path we took to get there i kind
of alluded to this
has implications uh we can think of that
as how the development process went so
you know if if this went really straight
and clean um you know we were just like
okay that was great that was easy right
if it was sort of like really messy and
kind of all the way around like you know
sort of uh
really circuitous or we had to backtrack
a ton of times you know maybe that was a
rougher development process
okay
the place we end up
is kind of how i think of like what
we've achieved right it's like the
quality like like i did this journey i
ended up somewhere and you know when i
get there i know you know this is kind
of why it's a navigational process with
software it's like i don't necessarily
know exactly what the thing will be at
the end sometimes i don't even really
know at all what the thing will be at
the end but i will know like when i get
there or when i get close enough to it
right and that's why it's a very
navigational process because much like a
kind of function where you can only
evaluate it at points and you can't
predict really what it's going to be
very well
we just kind of only know did we you
know if we're setting from if we're
trying to go from south america to
africa right
we will probably know when we hit land
but before then we may not really know
how it's going but we will know when we
get there and when we talk to the people
there we'll be like is this africa and
they'll be like yes right or something
right so we'll kind of know when we get
there but we won't necessarily know and
even when we actually get there we might
not know where we are exactly in that
area either like maybe we were aiming
for uh south africa and we end up in you
know up in egypt somehow or something
like this right so i kind of think of it
as this where we end up is sort of the
quality of the result
so what we're sort of seeing when we
talk about the bad code situation right
is in these processes i feel like we're
just getting horribly lost like we're
just kind of not only are we just like
kind of aimlessly creating these huge
routes through things that are very
wasteful and take way too much time and
all these other sorts of things but also
when we end up somewhere it doesn't
really seem to be very good like it
seems like we're kind of nowhere near
where we wanted to be right
and it feels this way sometimes too this
is another reason i like this analogy
someone's in the middle of a development
process or even at the end you're just
like oh man we totally lost our way like
like we can't even really see how we
would get there and furthermore another
reason that i like this analogy is
because it feels this way in the moment
too sometimes sometimes you're like i
just don't know
what we would do
to get past this like very it's like
it's very like intangible in that way
you can't quite put your finger on why
the code isn't coming out or what you
should do you're doing things that you
thought
right should get you further and they're
not or they're just knocking you back or
it just doesn't seem coming better it's
very like it feels like being lost in a
lot of ways
okay so in order to understand
why that
sort of
process might be going wrong
i want to put the blame
because i have an opinion about what is
to blame for this process going wrong
i just want to put the blame
on how we construct
that navigational process that filter
process in the brain of like navigating
what we're going to do
as we go code both institutionally and
individually how we do that
building up that part of brains i think
we're now doing a horrible job
in the old days the lack of resources
the 64k of the machine the fact that it
was a 6802 processor which could barely
do anything the fact that loads from
disc took you know eons
meant that that development of that
process in anyone's brain who could ever
get a program to work at all
they had already gone through the
process of actually being very aware
of what they were doing
everything they did
would either succeed or fail at all
based on whether the software was any
good right because even a slight bit of
being bad meant you couldn't get the
thing to work at all in such harsh
environments right it's sort of like if
the explorers were trained in the arctic
right
then all of them died who who weren't
really good or didn't learn really fast
right
so how are we doing this process now
well you know to a certain extent some
people are still doing it individually
and that tends to also be
highly coincident with people who maybe
aren't causing
quite so much of the uh the bad code
explosion but you know probably everyone
to a certain extent does work
individually and that's just you
naturally experiencing things there
isn't like an external force kind of
pushing at you there you're just playing
around and learning on your own
but the vast majority of these uh the
tuning that happens in those processes
now doesn't come from that because again
the resources are almost limitless there
and there isn't much of a weeding out
process that can really happen it's not
like on an old home computer that was
really difficult to use where you would
have to get good automatically because
otherwise you'd never be able to do it
or you just quit and go do something
else
so a lot of times where things come from
is like classes universities things like
that um it might come from like code
reviews or like mentors like there's a
programmer who ostensibly knows
something
and they're going to tell you that thing
or tell you what to do
um you know maybe your boss is really
mad and you get a bad performance review
or maybe he's really happy you need a
good one so you're calibrating based on
you know that was good that was bad i
don't know
you're gonna go read stack overflow
something like this right uh and you're
gonna look at what people said in there
you know what are the answers that are
voted up that's kind of like learning
what you know supposedly you're supposed
to do you go to lectures this lecture
for example right you're gonna listen to
someone talk and you know they maybe
they change your mind or maybe just
accept what they say maybe you're
critical of what they say i don't know
but you know you get some input that way
and it affects what's going on in here
and again
when i look at this i don't think we're
doing a terrible job when it comes to
like algorithms or stuff like that if
someone goes online and tries to search
for how to sort something
i don't necessarily think that they're
going to find like really bad
information all the time i don't think
that's going to happen you're probably
going to be able to find the resources
you need to learn how that sort of thing
works
so what i'm really talking about
is i'm talking about that other
style of code right the other the part
that's not the algorithm exactly itself
it's everything else it's all of the
infrastructure it's all that other stuff
that isn't really studied in the same
kind of way right we don't have order
notation for it or anything like that
and
pervasively like all throughout
everywhere in the industry what you will
see
is things that are sort of vague
statements
about the quality of that code
like it's clean right we're gonna we're
really washing the code like it's very
clean code if you do these things the
code will be clean right
this sort of thing
and what we see is people are taught
things
that are ostensibly going to make their
code clean
now they're never really taught
what clean code is
because nobody has a definition for
clean code
what they have is a series of things
you're supposed to do
in order to make the code clean
right like in other words we don't have
a thing that's like a program you run
that says yes clean code no not
right
what we have is things you're supposed
to do and then the code is clean that's
all we know
so you see acronyms like solid
this is taught a lot right
and if you look at the things on there
none of them
have any real world definition they're
not things that happen inside a computer
they're things that happen entirely in
your head
they are things that affect
what code you think you are allowed to
write that filter
is being trained
to use these metrics
which are largely fictional they're
imaginary metrics we came up with they
don't correspond to a
hard measurable fact of a cpu right so
we made them up
you're being trained not to write code
that would violate these or to write
code that would like evince these right
now lest you think i'm joking when i say
that this is something that people are
taught to do because some people are
like what are you talking about no one
teaches that well
literally when i went to go grab the
screenshot for stack overflow when i was
like uh gonna put a slide for that well
this was their blog right
so literally the day i happen to grab
the screenshot their blog is telling
people to do this on stack overflow the
place where people go to get programming
answers right
so
what these things
all have in common because solid's not
the only one there's plenty of other
things like this where we teach
clean code or try to convince people to
write clean code
what they all share is one very
important very bad characteristic and
that is they do not attempt to measure
anything
there is no measurement of anything
that we would actually care about
it's simply implied
that things we actually care about would
happen
if you follow these things
right
if you take your code
and you make sure
that it obeys the list off substitution
principle for all like classes that
could be substituted or something
nobody has any argument anywhere that
i've ever seen that suggests that that
actually improves some real world metric
that we've measured
the assumption
is that if you do that your development
process will take less time or be
smoother or have less bugs or something
the code will be cleaner it's just an
abstract statement
that if you do these things the code
will be cleaner and somehow
that will affect something you can
actually measure but we're never going
to say what that something actually is
or try to quantify it
now
i mean seriously look at these things
right is any of those teaching somebody
to actually think about a real effect
no
they're teaching people something
they're supposed to do
which is taking that filter and
modifying it
but it's not actually giving it any
actual guidance about like a metric or
something they're trying to accomplish
it's just wrote
now to me that's just like a ritual
right
if you're literally just saying like you
do these sets of things and the code is
clean it's very much like oh you know
like like we're gonna bless the food
before we eat it right
and these might make you feel better
and you may want to do them
but at the end of the day
they are not directly tethered to
anything we actually care about
rituals
may have served a purpose once or they
may never have served a purpose
and when we do them today what we're
largely doing is just doing them because
someone told us to do them they claimed
that by doing them we would get some
outcome but we're never really told
how those rituals were supposed to
really accomplish that we're just
supposed to assume that they do
now this is troublesome because
computers are actual things
the model in your mind of what i'm
targeting when i'm trying to make my
code and i'm trying to do that filter
that process the generator filter
process in my brain
if what i'm targeting
is solid
i'm by definition not targeting the
actual computer
right
the thing that i'm supposed to be
worrying about which is a computer that
runs this code is nowhere to be found in
that acronym right it's not there
anywhere
furthermore i'm not measuring my
development time solid nowhere in it
says hey by the way
actually these are all just supposed to
save development time so if you end up
seeing that you're not saving
development time stop doing it right
nobody says that
right
so i don't want to give you a new
acronym
because i don't think it's very useful
but to underscore the difference between
that acronym and what i would have
expected to see the trite acronym be
i would expect it to be something like
this i even arranged it in a way you can
say warmed just like solid
and what this is is just say look
if we're gonna teach something that goes
up in the filter
what it should be
is the actual things that programmers
need to care about
and then if something like solid was
actually a good idea
you would be able to evaluate that very
effectively by caring about things we
actually do and to me those things are
writing the code
agreeing on code if we have to have more
than one person
reading code because not only did we not
write all the code usually but even if
we did we might forget what we wrote so
we have to be able to read it we're
still to modify the code the code has to
execute on hardware
and then we have to be able to debug it
right
now if you look at these things maybe
you would say argue is better because
like coders don't agree on stuff they
argue about stuff right but either way
whichever one you want to think of it
it's still the same acronym so you know
i made sure that would work
now each of these things is a cost right
that's what i'm talking about each of
those things is a cost
execution is a cost of the actual
computation it's the most important cost
the e right how much does it cost to
execute this thing on the end user's
computer they're the people who are
ostensibly paying us and we are wasting
their time if that cost is very high
because we've shipped them something
lousy right
the rest of the cost or development time
right and those affect the customer
because if we never get the code done or
if it takes us too long to fix problems
in the code or if it takes us too long
to add features that affects the
customer too so all of those things are
costs that we ostensibly care about and
while i would say maybe execution should
be prioritized they're all important
right you can't just focus on one of the
exclusion of the others so what you're
trying to do is figure out a way to
minimize all those costs and you kind of
want to minimize as many of them as you
can with maybe different weights on them
depending on what you care about most
but that's what you're doing
so again pretty simple right
i've never seen anything like this
you don't go to conferences and have
people say like look this is what we
should be caring about
let's try to evaluate things on these
any you know people maybe throw up their
hands and say well you can't possibly
measure these things yes you can
i mean it's very easy to measure how
many github back and forths people have
before they actually fix an issue
it's easy to measure how many meetings
you're having it's easy to measure how
long it took you to write this piece of
code right
we are an industry that does
an infinite amount of a b testing on our
users and yet somehow we don't seem to
think it's very important to actually do
like a b testing with any kind of
metrics on any of the stuff we claim
we're supposed to be doing right
so let's try to bring it back to
bad code where does it come from
well i tried to give you the analogy
programmers are explorers they're
starting from somewhere
and they have a vague destination in
mind that they've been told to get to or
that they picked
and they have to get there but they
don't have any real knowledge of where
it is
well in this analogy what we've done
with all the stuff i just said
is effectively instead of giving this
something like a compass we just give
them tools that don't make any sense
we're even like a hammer and a tape
measure or something like that right and
we're like here you go set off on this
journey here's a hammer
now the worst part about it is it's not
even as bad as giving someone a hammer
because the real world person would know
that the hammer was useless to throw it
away
we've told them that this hammer
is critical for navigation so they're
like trying to like hold it up to the
sun or something and figure out like
which directs they're going they have no
idea that we've given them tools that
are not even relevant to the problem
that they're solving they're not
actually tools that measure anything
they're just arbitrary we just gave them
to them and and said here you go right
similarly we spent all our time talking
about a map that doesn't exist
we're talking about things like liskoff
substitution principle as if that has
something to do with programming
now it has something to do with certain
ideas in certain languages that someone
hypothetically thought might be
important
but it's entirely fictional it's like
middle earth right
your lord of the rings might be a great
story
but if you actually need to get from
south uh south america to africa
it's not gonna help you to be thinking
about like where mortar is on a map
right
you have a mental model that's been
tuned for things that have nothing to do
with the actual stuff you're trying to
solve
so we shouldn't be surprised when like
new programmers
come up and they just do ridiculous
stuff and these things will not control
because
they had no metrics they had nothing to
tether them back
to what they were actually trying to
accomplish we basically made their
entire filter process be about things
that are different from the actual
things we want to achieve
what else would we expect
right
so i think in modern day
when you've gone up through that system
and you didn't have the luxury
or the hardship depending how you want
to look at it
of having to do programming in a
constrained environment
you end up thinking that things are
completely insurmountable you're like
you're like i don't know how we would
ever do
this program any differently than what
we're doing right it's got to be a
million lines of code and super slow and
buggy and well like like this is just
how it's done
you can't even envision what the other
thing is because you haven't ever been
given the tools to get there right and
furthermore you're going to do you're
going to have been taught a lot
that code reuse is good
well the problem is the code that you're
going to be reusing right
i mean that's like in the narrative the
analogy of navigation that's like base
camp right it's like starting out at a
camp that someone else made
well the problem is they were lost too
they had no idea where they are so
you're typically taking a library made
by somebody who didn't really know what
they were doing and that's your new
starting point right
so people who failed to get to a
destination that we wanted to go to
are now also the jumping off point and
this gets worse than libraries whole
languages
whole platform ecosystems are this way
so we're literally starting our
navigators off
already lost in the wilderness with no
chance of ever getting to the to the
actual place making it way harder than
it would have been if we just started
back in port originally right
but they don't know that
because we've never been measuring any
of this
so can this be fixed
i mean sure i think it could obviously
be fixed because we have examples in the
past of programmers being trained up not
to do these things right
and so i think the first thing we need
to do is like start talking about the
real world
whenever we're talking about something
conferences
programming language constructs all
these things
we should be talking about how it
actually affects the results
what construct a real argument for how a
number goes down in the cost category
right
we should be giving people tools like
the one i suggested that actually
measure something we care about not
something we just assume that we care
about because
that will lock it in right
all of these things are very much like
the sort of navigation base camp analogy
any time we start someone off from a
place that we haven't verified is
actually really good
we create a huge problem for all the
things they will do in the future right
and
when i
talk about things like that
what i'm saying is don't just say stuff
right don't just talk about
this is clean code
actually measure
have something we can measure
this produced less lines of code for the
same equivalent execution right
not it's less lines of code because if
it's less lines of code but it runs
worse that didn't help anybody this is
less lines of code it's easier for
people to read why not because we talked
about it and decided it was easier to
read
but because we actually checked when a
new person comes to the company they are
now able to read the code faster
it used to take a day for them to like
read this
part and come up to speed on it now it
takes two hours right
we can measure this stuff it's real
world stuff
right
and of course
start actually putting measuring the
performance of things people actually
knowing what the performance of
something should be
that should have been fundamental the
whole time right
the acronym solid should never be
allowed to exist
if it doesn't have like
p solid like performance right like
there should have been something about
how do any of these things that you're
doing affect the actual run time of the
program
so
again
this is just my take on it a lot of
these things are very difficult to prove
or disprove because we don't have
formalisms for them the way we do for
things like algorithms one of the
reasons algorithms are probably better
in terms of how far they've developed is
because we can test them more concretely
we have a language to talk about them
but i don't fundamentally think these
problems of the code that's not the
algorithm
are as impenetrable as we're making them
out to be
we just need to actually focus on
something we can point to something we
can measure
why does tensorflow take four hours to
build
or whatever it takes
nowadays why
that should not be happening
it does not do anything that complicated
right
so how did we get there
we can measure that we know what's going
on
and we know the kinds of things the
kinds of filter processes that we've
been putting in people's heads result
in code bases like that
we need to start
like actually nailing those down and
saying no
don't teach people to do these things
anymore they're producing obviously bad
results that we can measure because
it takes for our hearts to build right
we can tell
so
hopefully that gives a little bit of
perspective on how i think about where
bad code comes from
i wish i had an answer that was more
magical
but at the end of the day i really think
that bad code just comes from that one
simple failure
and that is we have stopped measuring
and talking about
what we actually want
and we are almost exclusively talking
about or measuring things that are
largely fictional
they don't
directly connect back
and once you make that jump
the next generation never knows about
the earlier part right they only see
solid
they don't know
that there's all these other things they
should actually have been thinking about
and solid was just someone's random idea
about maybe some good rules of thumb
but you'd never teach that as your first
thing right you'd always teach the
evaluation of real metrics first
that was the end of the lecture i hope
you enjoyed it uh like i said please
check out our kickstarter links in the
description below we'd love to send you
a graphic novel or two if you get a
chance we only have a few days left
because this is the end of our whole
promotional thing and the kickstarter
wraps up in like five days i think from
when this video will be posted so please
check it out if you get a chance there
will be one more video it's the q a for
this so after the lecture i took
questions uh from the actual employees
of the company uh to whom i was
presenting so i didn't want to put them
into the actual video so what it will
actually be is like i will summarize the
question like on a card and then i'll
answer it so you can see my actual
answers but without the actual people
who asked the questions but there were
some good questions so i wanted to
provide those as well so i'll be back
here uh for part two tomorrow until then
have fun programming everyone and i'll
see you on the internet